<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Performance | Venkatesh CM]]></title>
  <link href="http://venkateshcm.github.io/blog/categories/performance/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://venkateshcm.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-30T16:12:36+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://venkateshcm.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Venkatesh CM]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Performance Testing Web Applications]]></title>
    <link href="http://venkateshcm.github.io/2014/05/Performance-Testing-Web-Applications/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-02T00:00:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://venkateshcm.github.io/2014/05/Performance-Testing-Web-Applications</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What do we mean Performance of web application ?
Term performance of web application is used to mean several things but couple of things that people are primarily concerned with are</p>

<ul>
<li>Response Time
The time taken by web application to process request and return response. Applications should respond to requests (response time) with in acceptable time limit. If application is taking beyond the acceptable time, it is said to be non-performing or degraded.</li>
<li>Scalable
The web application is said to be scalable if by adding more hardware, application can linearly take more requests than before. Two ways of adding more hardware are

<ul>
<li>Scaling Up<br/>
increasing the number CPUs or adding faster CPUs on a single box.</li>
<li>Scaling Out
increasing the number of boxes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Scaling out is considered more important as hardware is getting cheaper compared to cost of higher configuration hardware (super computer). But increasing the number of requests that an application can handle on a single box is also important.</p>

<p>An application is said to be performing well if it is scalable with acceptable response time.</p>

<p>Response time and Scalability don&rsquo;t aways go together i.e. application might have acceptable response times but not scalable or application is scalable but does not have acceptable response times. We usually tend to strike a balance between scalability and response time to get acceptable performance of the application.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
